<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sea-mens invitation, with a passengers observation in some particular things which concern them that practice navigation. 1 Their remarkable deliverances; and the use they make of them. 2 Their tempting and provoking of God about the winde, which obeys the Lord. 3 Their abusing themselves and their liberty when they go a shoar, whereby the creature suffers. 4 Something in particular to the captains and masters, and to all their inferiour officers. 5 How little the sea-men (with the souldiers in the fleet) are profited by their chaplains that in the year do get several groats out of their wages. And a more excellent way of teaching shewn then that of their chaplains. / By a servant of the truth, and a lover of righteousnesse, called William Caton.</title>
            <author>Caton, William, 1636-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08671</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171117</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922073</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80922073</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2891:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sea-mens invitation, with a passengers observation in some particular things which concern them that practice navigation. 1 Their remarkable deliverances; and the use they make of them. 2 Their tempting and provoking of God about the winde, which obeys the Lord. 3 Their abusing themselves and their liberty when they go a shoar, whereby the creature suffers. 4 Something in particular to the captains and masters, and to all their inferiour officers. 5 How little the sea-men (with the souldiers in the fleet) are profited by their chaplains that in the year do get several groats out of their wages. And a more excellent way of teaching shewn then that of their chaplains. / By a servant of the truth, and a lover of righteousnesse, called William Caton.</title>
                  <author>Caton, William, 1636-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sailors --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sailors --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191821:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SEA-MENS INVITATION, WITH <hi>A Paſſengers Obſervation</hi> In ſome particular things which concern them that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe Navigation.
<list>
                  <item>1 Their remarkable Deliverances; and the uſe they make of them</item>
                  <item>2 Their tempting and provoking of God about the Winde, which obeys the Lord.</item>
                  <item>3 Their abuſing themſelves and their liberty when they go a ſhoar, whereby the creature ſuffers.</item>
                  <item>4 Something in particular to the Captains and Maſters, and to all their Inferiour Officers.</item>
                  <item>5 How little the Sea-men (with the ſouldiers in the Fleet) are profited by their Chaplains that in the year do get ſeveral groats out of their wages.</item>
                  <item>6 And a more excellent way of Teaching ſhewn then that of their Chaplains.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>They that go down to the Sea in ſhips, that do buſineſse in great waters, theſe ſee the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 107.23, 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And they ſhall teach no more every man his Neighbour, and every man his Brother, ſaying, Know the Lord; for they ſhall all know him from the leaſt to the greatest of them, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 31.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By a ſervant of the Truth, and a lover of Righteouſneſſe, called <hi>William Caton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:191821:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:191821:2"/>
            <head>The Sea-mens invitation, with a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingers obſervation.</head>
            <p>GIve eare O ye Sea-men; And liſten, O all ye that practice Navigation; Is there any men upon the face of the earth that hath more emminent deliverances from apparent perils then you? Is there any calling or imployment, wherein the Sons of men are exerciſed, that the wonders of the Lord are more evident, or do more frequently appear then in yours? Can any men that repleniſh the Earth, declare experimentally ſuch remarkable deliverances from death, as you can? hath not the ſentence of death been oftentimes paſſed by you upon your ſelves, when you have ſeen no viſible way to eſcape it? and even at the very time, hath not deliverance come from the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond expectation? what dreadful and boiſterous, terrible and tempeſtious ſtormes do you often meet withall by Sea, which were able to bring down the courage of the ſtrongeſt man among you, and to make his heart to faint, and his fleſh to tremble? and have not your eyes ſeen thoſe ſtilled by him whom the wind and ſeas obey? But conſider in the height of them, and in the midſt of your diſtreſs, when death was feared and expected, was not then amendment of life promiſed, and a full reſolution and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in your hearts to live more godly and righteouſly the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of your daies, if that the Lord would be pleaſed at that time to deliver you? and according to your deſire it hath come to paſſe, and your requeſt in that particular hath been granted, as many of you can witneſſe.</p>
            <p>But now mark and conſider what uſe you have made of the remarkable deliverances before mentioned, have you not been elevated and puffed up by them? have you not been the more
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191821:3"/>negligent and carleſſe in ſerving the Lord, thinking that he would deliver you as he had done, though you ſpent your life as you had done formerly? have you not often boaſted of them, &amp; vaunted your ſelves in making vain repetitions of them over your cups and pipes, &amp; do you not often times curſe yourſelves, and ſwear by your deliverer, when you are repeating of them as idle ſtories, rather then as remarkable deliverances? but hear oh ye deſpiſers of the Lords rich mercy, of his forbearance and long ſuffering, How are your promiſes performed to the Lord, which you made in your diſtreſſe, or how have you paid your vowes unto him? ſeeing that after the hardneſſe and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency of your hearts, you treaſure up wrath unto your ſelves, againſt the day of wrath, and Revelation of the righteous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, who will render to every man according to his deeds, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            <p>Moreover notwithſtanding your manifold mercies, and the remarkable deliverances that you have above other men, who is there amongſt the Sons of men, that exceeds many of you in iniquity, in licentiouſneſſe and Laſciviouſneſſe? alaſſe for you, that you ſhould thus requite the Lord, as if he were like unto your ſelves; Surely friends, out of the multitude of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes, and in his tender compaſſion hath he been pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you out of many external perils (which none beſides him could have done) and eminent dangers in which you had been overwhelmed long, ago had he not had commiſeration &amp; pitty upon you, who joines hand in hand to work wickedneſs, and doth rejoice in iniquity &amp; takes more pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs then in the Lord your deliverer, who hath no delight in the death of a ſinner, but rather in ſhewing mercy on thoſe that fear him, and work Righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>And be it known unto you O ye Sea-fairing men, that your iniquities exceed the ſins of many, who have not ſeen halfe of the wonders of the Lord, that you have been eye witneſſes of; How can ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe abound more among a people then it abounds among ſome of you? and how few are there among you that will appear nobly to reprove it, but will rather connive and wink at it, yea and joine with them that live in it, although there is a witneſſe for God againſt it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191821:3"/>in your conſciences, yet that is little regarded nor its reproofs; for if you did mind it and its reproofs, then would you rather reprove the evil in your companions then conſent unto it, and ſo thereby you become guilty alſo, even as he who ſees a thief, and conſents unto him; but oh be awakened to righteouſneſſe, if there remains yet any true zeal in you for God, and let wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe be expelled out from among you, that righteouſneſſe may take place in you, and this know that the ſpirit of the Lord God will not alwaies ſtrive with you; therefore learn to do well, and ceaſe to do evil, that truth and equity may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound among you, as ſin and iniquity hath abounded, then ſhall your light break forth as the morning, and your health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily; yea, then ſhall you call, and the Lord ſhall anſwer you, you ſhall cry, and he ſhall ſay here I am.</p>
            <p>One thing I have often obſerved among you (oh ye ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) and that is your tempting and provoking the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the wind; but let me aske you doth it ever blow, but its fair for ſome of you? as for inſtance, if the wind be Eaſterly, and ſome of you be in <hi>Holland</hi> ready to come for <hi>England,</hi> then the wind is good and fair for ſuch; and at the ſame time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, ſome of you may be in <hi>England</hi> ready to goe for <hi>Holland,</hi> but frets againſt the wind which obeyes the Lord, and when he pleaſeth he cauſeth it to come Weſterly, ſo that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes good for you alſo, but not the ſooner for your tempting of God about it. And if it continue not good untill you by it be brought to your deſired haven, alas, how will you then frowne againſt it, and provoke him whom it obeyes by your curſing and ſwearing, by your impatiencie and frowardneſſe? yet notwithſtanding, he who cauſeth the rain to fall upon the juſt and the unjuſt, he alſo maketh the wind to be ſerviceable to you all, without which none of you could ſail from Country to Country like as you do, though it might be juſt with the Lord (who is ſlow to anger) to cauſe the wind to be ſtill, and ſo thereby deprive you of the benefit of it, becauſe of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe for it, and your unworthineſſe of it; and this know that, if he ſhould bid or command it to be ſtill, you (if you were ten times more then you are) could not make it blow; for it will not obey you, but him that created it <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Lord
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191821:4"/>God of Hoſts is his name, who is daily provoked by you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this thing, and you chafe and ſret your ſelves about it when it is againſt you; but which of you by curſing and ſweaing by chafing and fretting your ſelves can make it blow as you liſt, though it bloweth where it liſteth, and as he pleaſeth whom it obeyeth? Were it not better therefore for you to be ſtill and quiet and content, conſidering that although it be not good for you in particular, yet it is good and fair for ſome that practiſe Navigation, who ought to have the benefit of it as well as you, although none of you have ever ſeen it good for you all at once, yet I believe there is none among you that hath ſailed upon the Sea half a year together, but that the wind hath been good for you at one time or another. And this I ſay concerning it, that it may teach you, who are diſobedient to him whom it obeyeth (to wit the Lord) who rebuked the wind, and ſaid unto the Sea, peace, be ſtill, and then the wind ceaſed and there was a great calm; but though you are by him forbidden to ſwear, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. yet you are more diſobedient to him then the wind, which ceaſed at his rebuke, but ſo do not you from ſwearing at his reproof. Hee ſaith love your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe you, &amp;c. But are not you diſobedient to him in thoſe things, and in many more which might be inſtanced? And therefore I ſay the wind may teach you, which ſometime ſome of you will curſe for obeying him, who ſaith bleſſe and curſe not; but your folly in this thing is mighty great, and the Lord he will judge you for it, and do not think that he'l hold you guiltleſs who curſeth that which he bringeth out of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuries, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.7. which in it ſelf is very good.</p>
            <p>And who amongſt men could more ſubſiſt without it then you, who ſometimes will ſeem thankful for it, when it ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies your wills, but if it croſs you, bow froward and impatient are you? fretting your ſelves and provoking him whom it obeyes when it croſſeth you; therefore conſider of this ye that go down to the Sea in ſhips, that do buſineſs in great waters, and learn to fear the Lord, who commandeth and raiſeth the ſtormie winde; Note, when ſtormie winds come (with which you are often offended, that it is the Lord that raiſeth ſtormy winds, and who alſo ſtilleth them, and him they do obey who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191821:4"/>maketh the ſtorm a calm, ſo that the waves thereof are ſtill: and then are not you glad when you are delivered from the rage of the proud ſwelling waves of the boiſterous ſea? but alas how quicklie then do you forget your vowes which you made to the Lord, when your hearts fainted and your ſouls melted becauſe of fear and trouble that was upon you in the tempeſtious ſtorme, when you were almoſt at your wits end? but O that you would now be perſwaded to pay your vowes to the Lord, and not to forget all his deliverances, nor yet his mercies and favours which he hath beſtowed upon you, then would he oftentimes for your ſakes rebuke the winds and the ſea, yea he would hear your cry in the time of trouble, and bring you out of your diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore be awakened to righteouſneſs, oh ye Sea-fairing men, and ceaſe from rejoycing in iniquity, and from take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, leaſt that the Lord cauſe the great deep to ſwallow you up, like as it hath done many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands before you, who have been Rebellious and diſobedient to the Lord whom the winds and the ſeas obey.</p>
            <p>Another thing hath been obſerved by others as well as my ſelf among you, and that is this (to wit) when you have been ſeveral moneths upon the ſea, (more or leſs) and that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you by the providence of God come well into a Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and being permitted to go a ſhore, either about your buſineſs, or to ſee your friends, or to refreſh your bodies, or the like, even at ſuch times do you moſt ſhamefully abuſe your ſelves, by drinking exceſſively until you make your ſelves more like beaſts then men; And thus you abuſe your ſelves and your liberty, and cometh thereby the more to be bereaved of it, and in all this the creature ſuffers, being made ſubject to this vanity though not willingly.</p>
            <p>But for the ſake of the weak, and of thoſe that are almoſt void of underſtanding among you, I ſhall ſhew you in three particulars how the creature ſuffers: Firſt, it may ſuffer by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral moneths upon the ſea, being kept with ſalt and dry victuals, and ſometimes great ſcarcetie thereof, not onely of meat, but alſo of drink, inſomuch that a cup of clear water with a cruſt of dry bread would be of great worth ſometimes;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191821:5"/>and ſuch a day ſome of you have ſeen. Secondly the creature ſuffers when you come a ſhore (even the very time when it ſhould be refreſhed,) by your exceſſive drinking &amp; intemperate eating, you not being wiſe enough to govern your ſelves in ſuch a condition, when your ſtomackes will not bear much meat, partly by reaſon of the long ſcarcety, nor your heads much ſtrong bear, having drunk little for a long time before; thus the good creatures of God being abuſed by you, you through the abuſe of them become worſe then you were when you had need of them. Thirdly, when you have ſo abuſed your ſelves, with wine, ſtrong-waters or ſtrong bear, then can you not govern your ſelves, but oftentimes doth that which you ought not to do, and thereby tranſgreſſeth the Law a ſhore, or the orders you have a board upon your ſhip, and then it may be one puniſhment or another is inflicted upon you (if the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers neglect not their duty) whereby the creature is made to ſuffer; And then after your drinking exceſſively, you are for a time unfitter to do your buſineſs then you were before you went aſhore; and then peradventure by reaſon of your abuſing your ſelves and others, you may come to be debarred of the liberty of the going a ſhore, to take the benefit of the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Aire, and to be refreſhed with ſuch things as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try do afford, which you may have need of, and yet want them aboard.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Captains and Maſters of all Ships, and to all their inferiour officers.</head>
               <p>HAd you been guiltleſs of thoſe ſins whereof the Sea-men (whom you are ſet over) are guiltie, then you ſhould have been a terrour to them that do evil, and much of the evil which abounds amongſt them would have been ſuppreſſed by you, who are Authorized to rule over them; but much of your authoritie you loſe by partaking of their ſins; for behold, doth not the witneſſe of God in your own conſciences accuſe you, and tell you, you are inexcuſable your ſelves, foraſmuch as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191821:5"/>you are overtaken with thoſe ſins your ſelves which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them for? But conſider, ought you not to have been good patterns, and examples of righteouſneſs among them? ought you not to have walked in the fear of God among them, and endeavoured to have kept them in the ſame? ought you not rather ſharplie to have reproved them for their evil, then to have joined with them in the evil, as oftentimes many of you do? and have done, when you ſee they cannot govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ought not you therefore to govern them? wherefore are you Authorized and ſet as Maſters and Captains over them, if not to govern and order them? But how can you do that when you are inflamed with wine, ſtrong waters or ſtrong bear? and at ſuch times your weakneſs and nakedneſs doth appear unto them, and if you reprove and puniſh them for being as you are, then the Lord by his witneſſe doth judge, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you; for you being guilty, the Lord will not acquit you, neither ſhall you go unpuniſhed; but this I would have you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that whilſt you are guilty of thoſe things for which you reprove them, you cannot reprove them with that authority and boldneſſe you might do it if you were clear your ſelves of thoſe things for which you reprove them, neither is your reproof and puniſhment ſo effectual to them as it might be, if you were free from that for which you reprove and puniſh them; but alas what is that ſin among them that you are free from? And therefore cannot their tranſgreſſions be reproved by you as they ought to be, untill you have ceaſed from your own. And this I ſay, if you were but faithful unto the Lord in what you know, you might be inſtruments of good among them whom you rule over; but while your converſation is ſo vain, your carriage ſo light, your behaviour ſo wanton, and your words ſo unſavoury, there is little hope of their reformation who follow you for examples; Oh therefore be awakened to righteouſneſſe that you may be patterns of righteouſneſſe to thoſe that thirſt after it, if there be any ſuch among you: and grieve not the holy ſpirit no longer, which daily, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretlie reproves you, the reproofs of which hath been ſet at nought by many of you, as it appeares by your continuance in the reproveable things for which you are reproved, and theſe few lines are to you Captaines and Maſters, with your inferiour
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191821:6"/>Officers, not to upbraid ye, but to reprove you to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that you may come faithfully to diſcharge your dutie in thoſe things which are committed to your charge and truſt, for which you are not onelie to be accountable unto man, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo unto the Lord, who will render a reward to everie one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deeds done in the bodie, whether they be good or evil.</p>
               <p>And as for you who have Chaplains aboard with you, whom you look upon to be Miniſters of the word, and whom you own as teachers; This I have to ſay unto you in general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, That if they were ſent of God to preach his word, and to teach you, then they would preach freelie without coveting your groats or diminiſhing from your wages.</p>
               <p>Are they not of that ſort of whom the Lord ſpeakes by his Prophet <hi>Malachi, Mal</hi> 3.5. and ſaith I will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt thoſe that oppreſſe the hireling in his wages, ſeeing they muſt have a groat in the moneth out of your wages, and hath the ſame wages allowed them that you have; mark, do you not work harder for your wages, and take more paines for the ſame then they? then judge you whether this be equal or not that they ſhould have of your wages, for which you were hired, not being content with as much as muſt ſerve you who are worthie of your hire, and its pitty that you ſhould be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by them hirelings, who it may be may have two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groats in the moneth one of them more then one of you, If they did not come more for the love of your groats, then out of love to your ſouls, its probable that the ſame wages might ſerve one of them, that ſerves one of you.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if there be a hundred men in one Frigot more then in another, will not they ſeek to get into that Frigot where there is moſt men? and is not this one of their ends that they aime at, <hi>(viz)</hi> ſo manie more men, ſo manie more groats in the moneth? And here they reſemble their brethren the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh teachers who will ſtrive to get that pariſh Church (as they call it) where there is moſt Tithes, or the greateſt benefice: Now I ſay ſuch are not Miniſters of the Goſpel, neither doth the Lord ſend ſuch to preach his word; therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191821:6"/>cannot they profit you at all: And again if they were Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the word, or appointed of God to teach you, then they ſhould be good examples to you, which they are not in their pride, in their covetouſneſs, and in their oppreſſing you in your wages, neither are they good examples to you, in their intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate drinking until they be inflamed, nor yet in their light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and wantonneſſe by which they cauſe you to erre: And are not they inexcuſeable for judging and reproving you for theſe things whilſt they themſelves are guiltie of the ſame? But ſome will ſay that after they are rejected upon the Land, they will ſerve poor ſea-men; And when you have them, what are you benefited by them? or what difference is there in your life and converſation that hath them, and theirs that have them not? hitherto I have perceived none; for wickedneſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe abounds, both among you that have them, and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that have them not. Therefore in love to your Souls am I moved to ſhew unto you a more exellent way of teaching then theirs, which ſhall be free without monie and without price.</p>
               <p>Heare now then O ye Sea-fairing men who practice Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, have you not been ſometimes in jeoperdie of your lives? yea, have not your hearts ſometimes fainted, and your ſouls e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven melted, (as it were) within you, by reaſon of the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of fear, and trouble that hath been upon you in perillous and tempeſteous ſtormes? And hath not there ſome thing even at that verie moment of time been awakened in you, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you have in meaſure ſeen the wickedneſs of your condition, and the ſins of your youth? now that which was thus awakned in you, was Gods witneſſe, or the light which Chriſt Jeſus (the Son of God) hath enlightned you with all, which from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth (if you had obeyed it) it would have taught you the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of your life to have lived godlily, righteouſly and ſoberly in this preſent evil world, it would have taught you to have forſaken drunkenneſſe, pride covetouſneſſe, lying, ſwearing, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpeaking, yea in few words it would have taught you the whole dutie of man, which is to fear God and keep his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; And this is that teacher, the excellencie of whoſe teaching excels your Chaplines; For they teach you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191821:7"/>that the Scripture is the light, and the word and the power of God, but this will teach you to believe that he is the light,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.39. Rom. 1.16.</note> and the word of whom the Scripture doth teſtifie, and that the Goſpel is the power of God according to the Scripture; They will teach you by an hour glaſs, it may be two or three hours in the week, but this teacher will not be limited to an hour, to a time, nor yet to a place, but is alwayes preſent with you to teach you the fear of the Lord.
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> They through their Miniſtry may keep you alwayes learning, and yet not be able to bring you to the knowledge of the truth; but they who are taught by this, come to the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus; this teacher will teach you freely without money and without price; but your Chaplaines muſt have a certain ſum of money, otherwiſe many of them would lay down their trade of Preaching. This will teach you to ſing with the ſpirit and with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.15.</note> but they will teach you to ſing <hi>Davids</hi> conditions, which he paſſed through, and which many of you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gand not;
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.22.</note> This will teach you to pray with the ſpirit and with underſtanding; but they will teach you to pray formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at ſet times, as if the ſpirit were limited to a form, and the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to a ſet certain hour; This will teach you to ſhun evil in its appearance, to avoid the pollutions of the world; and to forſake ſin, and to abſtain from it, but they will teach you that you cannot eſcape the pollutions of the world while in the world,
<note place="margin">Prov. 14.34.</note> but that you muſt be polluted with them; neither that you can be free from that which is a ſhame (or a reproach) to any people; they will teach you to contend againſt that which reproveth you for ſin and condemneth it in the fleſh (<hi>viz.</hi> the light in your conſcience:) But it will teach you to love it, to obey it, to follow it, though it judge you, and reprove you, it is for your good, that you by it might be brought out of the things for which you are judged and reproved into peace with God who teacheth his people by this teacher, whoſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by it is a more excellent way of teaching then mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; which many in theſe latter dayes have received by tradition, of which ſort your Chaplaines are who oppreſs you in your wages; and teacheth for doctrines things which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191821:7"/>they ought not for filthy lucres ſake;
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.3.</note> as in thoſe particulars before mentioned you may ſee which briefly I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, but many more might be alleadged whereby it might be more evidently manifeſted that the way by which God teacheth (in the light) doth far excell the teachings of your Chaplains;
<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.27.</note> and this teacher whereof I ſpeak is that which teacheth of all things, which is truth, and no lie, which abode in the Saints and abideth in them, and as it taught them, ſo were they to abide in him who is light, Chriſt Jeſus, and then they needed neither Prieſt nor Chaplain nor any man to teach them, and they that come to witneſs the teachings of this teacher (the annointing) they need not ſay one to another, know him who hath promiſed to teach his people himſelf, even him whom the winds and Seas obey; for ſuch comes to know him and his teachings, even from the leaſt to the greateſt.</p>
               <p>Now if you would come to know this excellent way of teaching, you muſt come to the light which ſheweth you ſin and evil, and convinceth you of the ſame, and then you'l come to know its teachings, guidings and leadings, love it, and you love Chriſt; believe in it, and you believe in Chriſt, obey it, and then you'l obey him whom the winds and the ſea obey, therefore be not rebellious and ſtiff-necked, O ye that ſail upon the great deep, but turn you unto the Lord at his reproof, who ſecretly oftentimes doth reprove you for your ſin and tranſgreſſion whereby you have been long ſeparated from God, who doth not delight in the death of a ſinner but rather in ſhewing of mercy.</p>
               <p>O that you would be wiſe and learn to fear the Lord, then ſhould I with thouſands more rejoyce in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; And this I know, that there are ſome among you which is daily burthened with the wickedneſs that abounds among you, and yet ſcarce dare to reprove you, finding ſo much in themſelves that is reproveable, but if ſuch do keep to the light whereby that which is reprove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able is manifeſted, they will come to feel the oppera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the ſpirit of judgement and of the ſpirit of burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in themſelves, whereby they will come to be purified, and then they may freely reprove that in another which is judged and condemned in themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:191821:8"/>
               <p>Truly (O ye ſea-fairing men) my ſoul pitpittieth you,
<note place="margin">Iſay 57.20.</note> when I conſider that you are like the troubled Seas which caſteth up mire and dirt, your mirth and you melody, your jeſting and your folly, your laughter, and your vanity, your paſtime and your ſinging, your ſtorming &amp; your raging ſometime againſt the wind, &amp; ſometime one againſt another, alas what is it more then the mire and the dirt, or the foam of the troubled Sea which is your figure: I have alſo obſerved that it is hard to find a grave ſolid ſober man in a ſhip that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſs, but upbraiding and provoking one another to naughtineſs and folly; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie of that is to be found among you, as if you ſhould not be called to an account for it; but O! let the time paſt ſuffice wherein you have done very fooliſhly, and now learn to fear the Lord; and let the wind and Sea (which you have ſo much accaſion for, teach you to obey him, who hath more delight in obedience to his voice, then in burnt-offerings and ſacrifices.</p>
               <p>This is the day of your viſitation wherein the hand of the Lords love is ſtretched out towards you,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> and wherein he is waiting to be gracious unto you, therefore now in this the day of the Lords everlaſting power, ſeek ye the things which belong to your peace, while they may be found, leaſt the day come wherein they may be hid from your eyes; in love to your ſouls is this Paper write and ſent among you as a token of Gods viſitation to you, from one who hath view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your condition, and was moved with commiſeration and pitty towards you who now hath time, but how long you may have it you know not; therefore while you have it, prize it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Amsterdam in Holland</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>Mon.</hi> 1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>W. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:191821:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THe mighty day of the Lord is coming, and he will teach his people himſelf, who is gathering his people, from all falſe ſhepherds, and Chriſt Jeſus the great Shepherd, ſhall rule over them and teach them who will write his Law in their hearts, and put his Law in their minds, and he will be their God, and they ſhall be his people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. and his annoiting ſhall be in them, and as that doth teach them they ſhall abide in the Son, and in the Father, and his ſpirit in them ſhall lead them; and as that doth lead them, they are the Sons of God; and it ſhall lead them into all truth, and it ſhall comfort them, and bring all Chriſts words to their remembrance which he hath ſpoken forth, and that ſpirit is it that doth reprove the world, which is the Saints Comforter, therefore to that, that doth reprove you all, muſt you come before you know the Comforter.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
